Welcome back to Apush in under three
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. So back over in America, even
though the economy was booming by the
60s, people start realizing that not
everyone is benefiting. A book that
acted as a very good expose was The
Other America by Michael Harrington.
Basically, this book revealed that there
was a hidden poverty in America,
revealing the struggles of millions of
poor Americans. And then on top of this,
because of the result of World War II
and the economic boom of the 50s, by the
1960s American citizens have almost full
confidence in its own liberal government
and thinks the government can solve
social issues. This will all lead
President Lyndon B. Johnson to enact his
Great Society, which was an expansion of
the New Deal focused on social issues
rather than just the economy, aiming to
end poverty, reduce racial inequality,
improve education, and expand health
care. Let's go over the things the Great
Society created. Programs focusing on
poverty will be implemented, such as the
Job Corps for job training, Head Start
for early childhood education, and the
Food Stamp Act for food assistance.
Health care programs will also be
implemented, such as Medicare for the
elderly and Medicaid for the poor. It's
also important to note that this plan
for a Great Society often worked
alongside the ongoing Civil Rights
Movement at the time. The other part to
this though is immigration, and we see
this with the Immigration Act of 1965,
where finally quotas are removed,
meaning we see a lot more immigration
from Latin America and Asia, which
permanently changed US demographics. So
you might be asking now, was this Great
Society a good success or bad overall?
Well, it obviously did have successes
that we still see in our society to this
day, but I want you to understand
something. Remember the Gilded Age,
where America had a very small
government and didn't intervene in its
economy at all? Remember the whole
laissez-faire thing? Now we have gone
through the New Deal, World War II, and
now the Great Society. So the result is
the US government is as big as it has
ever been, and it is intervening as much
in its own economy as it ever has.
Conservatives on the right will argue
that the government is way too big now.
And later past the 70s into the 80s,
things like Vietnam and a lot of
government spending will cause mass
inflation and unemployment leading to a
growing distrust in government and a
resulting age of conservatism, but I get
ahead of myself. On the screen now are
AP style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.